I haven't updated in the past few days.
我因为我前几天一直没更啊
A lot has happened recently.
最近发生了很多事
So, I'm starting to update today.
所以啊今天开始更呃
What exactly has happened?
发生了什么事呢
Actually, I recently bought a motorcycle.
其实就是我最近呢买了一辆摩托车
And then I also purchased a car.
然后呢我又买了一台汽车
These two events happened within a week.
短短的这两件事情发生在一个星期里边
I spent about 10,000 yuan on the motorcycle.
然后我买摩托车呢大概是花了1万块钱
And I spent roughly the same amount on the car.
买汽车呢大概也是花了1万块钱啊
I'll explain the details in the video.
具体怎么回事
I'll tell you all about it in the video.
我会在视频里边给你们说的啊
The updates were quite slow a couple of days ago.
就是前两天更的很慢啊
But I've been taking care of the kids these past two days.
这两天带孩子
Then the car thing
然后弄车的事儿
The motorcycle thing took quite a while to sort out
弄摩托车的事儿就折腾了半天
Then my car was bought from the second-hand car selling website, Guazi
然后我的车是在瓜子二手车那个售卖网上买的
I originally planned to buy from Zhuanzhuan
本来想在转转上买啊
But I ended up buying from Guazi
但是我就在瓜子二手车买上了
It was pretty good, though
嗯还是可以的啊
Not advertising for any platform
不是给任何的平台打广告
Just saying, both Zhuanzhuan and Guazi are fine options The car inspection was great They are all pretty good platforms. And there's really no favoring one over the other. The cars I looked at before were all new. I checked them out on Dongchedi and Autohome.
就是说这个反正呵呵转转跟那个瓜子都可以 验车都不错啊 还都是不错的平台 然后其实也没有什么厚此薄彼啊 我之前看的车都是一手车 是在懂车帝上和汽车之家上看的
Oh, each one introduces their products as if they're not advertising at all.
哎每一家都介绍就相当于没打广告啊
I'm not an automotive UPloader myself.
啊我也不是汽车区的up主
But I do know a few automotive UPloaders.
我跟几个汽车区的up主倒真认识
When I talked to them,
但是我跟他们一说
about the car I bought later on.
我买了什么车以后
They all ignore me now.
他们都不理我了
Hehe, maybe because they think the car I bought is too shabby.
呵呵可能因为觉得我买的车太破败
It’s indeed quite so.
确实比较啊
It’s not really cheap, just 10,000 yuan.
廉价倒不是真的1万块钱
But the total price is 34,600 yuan.
就是它的总价呢是3万4600块钱啊
If you were to buy a new one, though,
当然他如果你要买新的的话
it would cost around 40,000 yuan.
大概是4万多块钱啊
But generally, dealers offer discounts.
但是一般商家都会有折扣
But it's over 40,000 though
但是4万多呃
The reason it's around 30,000
之所以是3万多呢
is because if you depreciate it further
因为你现在如果再折旧
and factor in the depreciation of the car
再把这车折出去
it can still be worth 20,000
他还能折2万块钱
So in essence, for this car
等于说这车呢
I actually only spent about 15,000
实际上我只花了大概1万5000块钱左右吧
Of course, you have to account for various expenses like insurance and so on
当然你要算上各种各样的要保险啊什么之类的
So the final cost will definitely exceed this figure
这个最后这个费用肯定就超过这个数了
But it’s still quite affordable.
但是仍然是很便宜的一个啊
A very reasonable price.
一个价格啊
I initially planned to buy one for around 5,000 yuan. A 6,000 yuan replica of the Suzuki UY125. But in the end, I went for the genuine Suzuki 125. I got it from a dealership. The dealership, you see, can handle everything for you, and as you know, I live in one of the six central districts of Beijing.
我本来想买5000多块钱 6000块钱的那个仿的铃木的UY125的车 后来我还是买了铃木125的正版 我在一个车行弄的 因为车行呢他呢给你大家知道我是那个城六区
A household registration in the six central districts of Beijing can only be registered under a company.
北京城六区的这个户口只能上公户
Did you know that?
你知道吗
My company is located in this suburb.
我的这个公司在这个郊区啊
But the reason I moved it to the suburb was to facilitate supply deliveries.
但是呢就是我就是为了上供货
I specifically registered the company in the suburb for the motorcycle.
摩托车才特意去的郊区重新注册的公司啊
Of course, I've had my motorcycle license for three years now.
当然我拿摩托驾照都已经3年了
And I've had my car license for five years.
拿汽车驾照都5年了啊
So why did I suddenly change my mind recently?
最近为什么突然改变了想法呢
Actually, the car I got is from a recent event.
其实我拿的这个车标呢
It was on May 28th of this year.
是最近今年5月28号的事
I was in the family waiting list.
我是家庭排队
Then there's the family's new energy vehicle.
然后排的是那种家庭的新能源啊
Compared to the gasoline car,
跟那个油车
the chance of getting a gasoline car is quite low.
那油车抽中的概率很低啊
As a family in Beijing,
作为北京的家庭
but we managed to get a spot for a new energy vehicle through the waiting list.
但是呢排队呢排新能源车就排到了啊
Beijing's new regulations for 2025
北京2025年的新规定
stipulate that only pure electric vehicles qualify as new energy vehicles.
是只有纯电车才算是新能源车啊
We previously considered a range extender,
之前想买增程
and were also thinking about a hybrid.
想买混合动力啊
This won't work.
这都不行了
So there's no way out.
所以就没辙啊
We can only say goodbye to BYD Qin L. And say goodbye to DDM and the like. There's nothing we can do. Actually, I was really considering a range-extended model. One that has a bit of battery capacity. So it can run on pure electric or gas.
就不能跟只能跟比亚迪秦L 就DDM之类的说拜拜了啊 没有办法 其实我本来挺想买那种就是增程式的 然后自己带一点电 然后可以纯电也可以加油
That way, the combination of electric and gas would significantly increase the range, right?
这样呢加油加纯电能不是能续航很多吗
What really matters to me when buying a car is the range.
我其实买车最重要看的是续航
Like, when can I refuel again?
就是什么时候可以再加一次油啊
I recently got this UI model,
我现在买了这个UI
after the 125cc version,
125以后呢
this is a motorcycle shop.
这是摩托车行
after they helped me take care of all these things,
帮我把这些事都给办了以后呢
it’s roughly added a secondary fuel tank.
大概是加了一个副油箱
The main fuel tank is 6 liters.
它本身的油箱是6L
The secondary tank is 10 liters.
副油箱是10L
On a full tank, it can run 700 kilometers.
加满油的状态下可以跑700km啊
That's an impressive range.
非常彪悍的一个续航
So, the Geely Panda Knight I bought now,
所以我现在呢买的这个吉利的这个熊猫骑士啊
the original owner had only driven it 6 kilometers,
它是呃原车主开了6km啊
basically like new, 0 kilometers.
基本上是0km
The second-hand car is in excellent condition.
二手车非常新啊
It was first used by a female owner.
女生一手用呃
So, I'm not particularly concerned about the range.
所以他的这个我就不是特别重视续航
As everyone knows, my electric car has a range of 100 kilometers.
因为大家知道我的电动车续航是100啊
My electric bike still uses a lead-acid battery, not a lithium one.
我的纯电瓶的电动车还不是锂电的
My No. 9 mz mix is a lead-acid battery model, after all. And I don’t plan to switch to lithium batteries in the future. I just prefer the lead-acid batteries. Anyway, I replace them every one or two years. Then it costs about 1,000 yuan after depreciation, right? Even with the depreciation cost, replacing it would still be around 1,000 yuan.
我的9号mz mix就是电瓶款嘛 然后我以后也不打算换锂电 我就想电瓶 反正一两年就换一次 然后就1000多块钱再折旧对吧 还有那个折旧的费用再换过来也就1000多
So, to sum up,
所以来讲的话
you should buy a large single-cell battery.
你买一个大单体电池
Spending four or five thousand might not be necessary.
大概四五千就有点没必要啊
Besides, buying a large unit also carries the risk of fire.
再说买大单体也有失火
There's also the risk of losing control.
也有这个失控的风险
Moreover, the charging time would be quite long.
而且这个充电的时间就会很长
So, I decided to go with a battery instead.
所以我决定还是用电瓶吧
Why does my car only have a 200-mile range?
然后我汽车为什么续航才200呢
Because I don't plan on getting on the highway.
因为我不打算上高速啊
Because my actual driving experience is practically zero.
因为我实际的驾驶经验几乎等于零呃
My motorcycle riding experience is also practically zero.
我的摩托车驾驶经验也几乎等于零
So I still consider myself
所以我现在仍然把自己看成是
a trainee in this field
实习期的这个选手啊
and no matter what
然后呢啊无论怎么样
it's just a bit
也就一点
of that experience from riding off-road motorcycles when I was young
那个就是之前小时候骑野摩托的经验
plus the experience with electric scooters
再加上这个这个这个这个电瓶车的经验
so it's not enough to
所以这个东西呢不足以啊
shake things up
这个撼动一切
because back then, we were all pretty timid
因为那时候小时候都是怂嘛
I haven’t driven much on this motor vehicle lane.
都没怎么在这个机动车道上开嘛
Just driving around for fun.
就随便开着玩一玩
It’s borrowed from a friend.
借朋友的这种
So, this bit of experience can’t really count as actual driving experience. But I think it’s pretty good. Why did you buy one with such low range? Because it’s basically sufficient for use within Beijing. And this Panda Knight can be charged slowly, unlike the Wuling Hongguang.
所以这点经验不能算作真实的这个驾驶经验 然后呢我感觉这个东西就挺好 为什么买续航这么低的 因为在北京市内基本够用了 而且他这个熊猫骑士呢又能不像五菱宏光
It can also be charged slowly.
它又能慢充
It also supports fast charging
又能快充
It can charge up to 100% in just 0.51 hours
快充的时候0.51小时就能充到百分之百
So in Beijing, it’s hard to get around
所以在北京这个地方呢四处都开不动啊
But it doesn’t really matter
然后呢也是无所谓
When it comes to highways
这个这个上高速啊
My 125cc motorcycle can go on the highway
我摩托125的上高速能上
But I can’t handle such high speeds
但是自己承受不了那么快的速度啊
Cars can also go on the highway
汽车也是能上
But the range is quite short
但是续航很短
I'm afraid of breaking down on the highway
我怕趴窝在高速上
So I set a rule for my brother
所以我给弟弟定了一个原则
which is to avoid highways
就是不上高速
Of course, national roads can be just as dangerous
当然国道呢一样危险
But I don’t go on long motorcycle trips anymore
但是我也不进行长途摩旅了
Right?
对不对
If I really go on a motorcycle trip
我要是真是出去摩旅
I’ll send the bike by logistics first
我就把车先物流先发过去
And if I’m going to places like Tibet or Xinjiang
然后如果要是去西藏新疆这种地方
I'm pretty sure
我十有八九
If I really want to go on a road trip
如果真想自驾游的话
I would rent an off-road vehicle there
我也会在当地租越野车啊
Of course, I don't have any off-road driving experience
当然来讲我也没有越野车的驾驶经验
But I can go with others
那就可以跟别人一块玩
And life doesn't necessarily have to be about motorcycle travel
而且人生不一定非要去摩旅啊
Right?
对不对
So buying a motorcycle for me is about fulfilling a wish Since I've already got my license anyway Right? You should have your own motorcycle at some point. Isn't it? Otherwise, you'd always be borrowing others' official vehicles. That's not very meaningful, is it?
那我买摩托来讲就是完成一个心愿 就是呃反正也学了驾照了 对不对 你总得拥有一辆自己的摩托 是不是 要不然以前老借着别人的公务车开 也没有什么意思啊
Back then, I borrowed from friends to make videos.
自己当时为了做视频
Yeah, just borrowed from friends.
就是啊那个跟朋友借
It doesn't really make sense.
那也没有什么意义
So, speaking of it,
所以来讲的话
I actually haven't made any videos about motorcycles.
我其实也没拍过摩托车的视频
I think it's really dangerous to ride a motorcycle while filming.
我觉得一边骑摩托一边拍视频的时候很危险啊
A lot of bikers have died this way.
好多机车员都是这么死掉了啊
You know, most of the bloggers in the motorcycle section.
就是你看基本机车区的那些博主
Well, now maybe only one in ten is left.
呵呵现在十不存一吧
So I wonder why I suddenly wanted to buy a motorcycle.
所以我觉得嘶我本来为什么突然想买摩托车呢
I probably got the idea from watching Ha Nai Pi's motorcycle trips.
我可能是因为看了哈奶皮在摩托摩旅啊
He went on a motorcycle journey right after getting his license.
然后他是刚拿本就出去摩旅了
And he bought a street bike.
还买的是街车
I just think it's really bold.
我就觉得哇胆子真的挺大的
And indeed, life should be enjoyed early.
然后确实啊人生应该确实应该早点享受人生
But then, you see me spending my limit of 10,000 yuan on a motorcycle,
但是呢大家看我极限的1万块钱买摩托车
10,110 yuan on a car,
1万10块钱买汽车啊
which actually cost over 30,000 yuan.
实际上是花了3万多
But if you add the insurance,
但加一起你把保险加一起
all the miscellaneous expenses together,
乱七八糟都加一起啊
it still doesn't exceed 50,000 yuan, right?
加一块也没超过5万块钱对吧
Uh, everyone, don't follow my extreme frugality. Well, extreme frugality, you know, doesn't actually lead to a particularly good experience, does it? Your life experiences won't be as fulfilling. You all know I used to advise people to save money,
呃大家不要学我这么极致的节省啊 嗯极致的节省的话呢 你就没有反而有特别好的体验对吧 就是说你的人生的体验就会不会特别好 大家知道我以前都是劝人家省钱的
but in the past couple of years,
但是现在这两年
I've started to advise people not to be so frugal anymore.
我开始不是那么劝人家省钱了啊
Because I think young people should get out more,
因为我觉得年轻人还是应该多出去啊
go to bars,
去酒吧呀
attend concerts.
看演唱会啊
Well, going abroad for travel
呃出国旅游啊
buying a nice car
买好车呀
we should enjoy life
还是应该享受人生
after all, earning money isn’t easy
呃反正挣钱也不容易
so if you want to spend it, go ahead
就你们想花就花了呗
it’s no big deal
没关系
because my goals are different from yours
因为我跟你们的目标是不一样的
my goal is to never work a day in my life
我的目标是一辈子不上班啊
I actually haven’t worked for more than a month
我实际也没上超过一个月的班
If some of my experiences can be counted as work,
我如果有些班能算班的话
then that’s fine.
那也就可以
Because during the time I was actually getting paid,
因为我基本上真正的领工资的那段时间
I wasn’t sitting in the office every day,
也不是天天坐班
nor was it a 996 schedule.
也不是996
So most of the time, I was basically working in a relaxed state.
所以基本都是在休息的状态下进行的啊
So I can’t really say I’ve truly been part of the workforce.
所以我不能严格意义上说真正参与劳动过
Right?
对不对
So, to put it simply, everything has its own place.
所以来讲这就是呃一一码是一码
So I've decided that I never want to work for the rest of my life.
所以我决定呢就是一辈子不想上班
And it's not just me; I don't want to work for the rest of my life. I think about my son, my children. In the future, there might be more, but I feel one son is enough for me. I just hope that my child,
而且我不光自己一辈子不想上班 我想我儿子啊 我的孩子们啊 以后呢就是啊希望可能还有 但是不一定我觉得我有这一个儿子够了啊 就是我就希望我的孩子啊
can also have a life without ever having to work.
就是将来能够也一辈子不上班
So I pay special attention to saving money.
所以我会特别在意攒钱啊
Really cares about saving money
特别在意攒钱
Really cares about not spending too much
特别在意不花太多的钱
If some things can get by with the bare minimum
一些东西如果能用最低限度度过的话
Then just get by with the bare minimum
就最低限度度过啊
Now I've got the family quota
现在是拿到了家庭指标
If I don't buy a car within a year
一年之内不买车的话
They will definitely take the quota back
肯定是要给你指标收回的
So I had to buy a used car
所以我就不得已买了一个账号车啊
As you know, I don't commute either
大家知道我也不通勤
I don’t go to work
我也一不上班
and I don’t drop off my kids
二不送娃
right?
对不对
So, when it comes to it
所以来讲的话
I have absolutely no need for that
我是完全没有这方面的需求
Since I don’t have that need
既然没有这方面的需求
why would I buy a fancy car?
那我为什么要买好车呢
Whether I buy the Xiaomi 12 Ultra or the Xiaomi 12 7
无论我是买小米苏七还是买苏7ultra
or even the BYD Dolphin
还是买比亚迪的海豚
The Seal and Seagull series
海豹海鸥系列
I’ve actually seen them all
其实我都看过
I really want to buy the Seal
我挺想买海豹的啊
Not that I don’t want the Dolphin series
不是挺想买海豚系列的
The top-of-the-line Dolphin costs 120,000
海豚的顶配版12万
But I’ve already bought a car for 30,000
但我现在买了一个3万的车啊
I realized that what I truly like is money
才发现其实我真正喜欢的是钱
What I really love is a life without work
我真正喜欢的是不上班的生活
So for me, speaking of which
所以对我来讲的话
What size house you live in What kind of car you drive How beautiful your wife is, it doesn’t matter Because these things can only make me happy for a moment It’s very impressive It indeed is very impressive But no matter how big my house is I can’t possibly have people over for parties every day
住多大的房子 开多好的车 娶多漂亮的媳妇都没有用 因为这些东西我能高兴一时啊 很有面子 的确是很有面子 但是我住再大的房子 也不可能天天请人来家里边狂欢
No matter how beautiful my wife is
我娶再漂亮的老婆
I’m actually more concerned
我反而更担心
right?
对不对
even if I find the best car
我找再那个开再好的车子
my looks are what they are now
我现在颜值就这样
I drive a nice car
我开好车
that would be a waste of the car
那不是糟蹋车嘛
right?
对不对
so I think just having the experience is enough
所以我觉得就是只要有一种体验就行了
the motorcycle is the same
摩托车也是
I don't necessarily have to buy a 450cc street bike
我不一定非要买什么450的街车
or a 750cc sport bike
不要买什么750的仿赛啊
or a 1000cc BMW
一千一千cc的这个宝马
I don’t think I have that kind of luck
我觉得我没有那个命啊
Actually, I bought an Ultra
其实我买ultra啊
and another BMW with a Beijing A license plate
再买一个京A的宝马呃
I don’t really spend much cash right now
我现在现金来讲的话也消耗不了多少
But for me
所以但是对我来讲的话
the experience from these things is just a momentary thrill
就是这些东西的体验感是一瞬间的啊
Isn't that what life's all about, that one moment?
就是所谓的你这一辈子不就是为了啊那一下嘛
Right?
对不对
It's all for that moment.
就是为了啊
You spend a long time working for it,
那一下你要花很长时间去上班
earning money,
去赚钱
paying off loans. It's really not necessary. I even did the math before, whether to go for an installment plan. I originally planned to go for an installment plan that way, I could spend a small amount of money but I found out that with the installment plan even though it's only 619 dollars a month for five years
去还这个还这个贷款 很没有必要 我之前还算了一下 要不要做分期 我本来想做分期 这样可以花很少的钱 可是我发现做分期 虽然5年之内每月只能交619块钱啊
you still have to pay 30% upfront
这个然后呢呃呃第一次付这个30%
which is 13,000 dollars
首付1万300块钱
and in reality, you end up paying 13,000 dollars in interest
但实际上你要掏1万3000块钱的利息
that 13,000 dollars in interest is no small amount
这1万3000块钱利息也不少啊
right?
对不对
It accumulates to over 2,000 dollars in interest every year for five years.
搁着5年每年都2000多块钱的利息
So I think it doesn’t make much sense.
所以来讲我觉得就没有太大意义
If you insist on financing it,
非要去分期啊
I later thought that if you buy a house on installment,
所以我后来我就觉得那你们分期买的房
or a car on installment,
分期买的车
like I bought the Xiaomi Ultra,
比如说我花了一个买小小米ultra
I put down 150,000 as a down payment,
然后我首付15万
and the actual money I paid out,
然后我真正掏出来的钱
in the end, could be a very large figure.
可能到最后就是一个非常大的一个数字啊
When it comes to car loans,
因为来讲的话这个汽车贷款来讲的话
it's usually calculated at 18% or some other rate,
都得是按18%还是按多少来算的话
the amount you owe on Huabei,
实际上你欠的花呗
the credit card debt,
欠的信用卡
the car loan,
欠的车贷
the mortgage rate is quite high,
房贷的这个利率是很高的
especially the car loan rate is quite high,
特别是车贷的利率是很高的啊
but the mortgage rate has come down now,
这个房贷的利率当然现在是下来了
though you might only be able to afford a house once in your lifetime. For most people, you can probably afford to buy a house only once. You can't realistically buy two or three houses. If you do buy two or three houses, it means the housing prices where you bought them are relatively low.
但是你一辈子大概也只能买得起一次房哈 对一般人的人来说 你大概其也只能买得起一次房 你不可能说呃你买两三套之类的 如果你买的是两三套房 那证明你买房的地方的房价比较便宜
Places with low housing prices don't necessarily guarantee stable prices.
房价便宜的地方实际上是保证不了这个房价
Speaking of now,
现在来讲的话
major cities lifting purchase restrictions,
大城市放开限购
it will impact smaller cities.
他会把小城市
Small and medium-sized cities and towns
中小城市城镇
and the money from these counties is all drawn to the big cities
还有这个县城的这个钱都吸引到大城市来
ultimately, you'll find your opportunities
最终你会发现你的机会
your social mobility
你的这个阶层突破
your business endeavors
你的这个做生意的
these talents can only be realized in big cities
这个才能都是只能在大城市发挥
in small cities
小城市啊
they have already monopolized the local resources
他们已经会把那当地的资源就占据了
it's a society based on personal connections
那是一个人情社会
So you're completely impervious to any criticism or advice.
所以你根本就是针插不进水泼不进
Only independent men and women in big cities
只有在大城市独立的男性和女性
have a certain chance of surviving.
才有一定的机会在生存
This whole concept of health, elderly care, and consumption-oriented housing
他这套卫生养老消费住宅的这套东西
only makes sense in this context.
这个逻辑才成
So ensuring you have a large apartment in a small city
所以你保证小城市有大平层
isn’t really that useful.
其实没有太大用啊
So in a small city,
所以你在小城市呢
having a modest home for personal use is enough.
有一说自固的自住的房子就可以了
If you're investing, you should still consider big cities. It's still advisable to invest in major cities. That's just my personal opinion, though. Of course, it's not always accurate. No worries. You don't have to follow my advice. Anyway, this time it's about the Extreme Challenge of buying a car for 10,000 yuan.
大城市其实你还是应该就是如果你是投资的话 还是应该投资在大城市 这是我个人的见解啊 当然来讲的话不一定准啊 没有关系 你不一定非得听我的啊 呃总之嗯这次极限挑战1万块钱买车
Or buying a house for 10,000 yuan.
1万块钱买房啊
Not buying a house for 10,000 yuan, though.
不是1万块钱买房
Spent ten thousand yuan on a car
1万块钱买车
Spent ten thousand yuan on a motorcycle
1万块钱买摩托
But I managed to pull it off
还是挑战成功了啊
Pretty happy about it
挺高兴的
Actually, I didn't really need to buy the motorcycle
其实摩托本来可以不买
Could have gone for a cheaper one, a few thousand yuan one
也可以只买一个几千的
But once I learned CED, I just had to get a motorcycle
但是没办法学了CED就想买摩托
Couldn't help it
这也没有办法的事情
And the joy of motorcycle touring is irreplaceable
而且摩托的摩旅的快乐啊
The joy of being a biker is something
就是当黄毛的快乐
many people can't even imagine.
很多人是想象不到的啊
Ever since I got this motorcycle,
自打这个有了这个摩托以后呢
I now greet people and say,
就是啊我现在跟人就是一边打招呼
hey, if you're free, I can take you for a ride on my motorcycle.
就说哎有空那个带你骑我摩托之类的
Of course, many would say,
当然来讲那肯定很多人就说
if it’s a scooter,
那要是呃这个这个骑的是踏板的话
girls would definitely give it a second look,
肯定美女会侧目啊
or maybe even roll their eyes.
或会翻你白眼之类的
I don't care
我不在意
Is that right?
对不对
Why do I have to carry a beautiful woman?
我为什么一定要驮美女呢
Can't I carry my good friend instead?
呃是不是我托我好朋友不行吗
That's quite normal
这是很正常
And I think owning a car isn't that significant either
然后我觉得汽车的意义呢也不大啊
Once you truly own it You'll find it not very useful It's more of a burden I feel like I'm a burden now I still need to pick up that car and drive it back find a place to park it find a spot to park and make sure it doesn't get sunburned
你真正拥有了以后 你就觉得没有什么用 反而是累赘啊 我现在觉得已经是累赘了 还得把那车取了 还得把它开回来 还得找地儿停 找地儿停 还不能让太阳晒
I also need to buy some sun protection gear
还得买遮阳的设备
and after a while, when I go out
然后呢时间长了还得出去以后
I need to turn on the air conditioning first
我要先开空调
Then I have to find a parking spot
然后我去哪还得找停车位
And pay for parking
然后要交停车费
Not to mention maintenance
然后还要保养
Ugh, it's just so annoying
哎呦就觉得很烦
I just had to park my motorcycle at the designated spot today
我光动今天那个把我这摩托停到指定地点啊
This motorcycle repair
这个修摩托
Installing a GPS tracker on the motorcycle
那个给摩托装那个防盗GPS
Modifying the fuel tank
改油箱
Upgrading the trunk and adding a guard bar
改后备箱加护杠
Then, going to the vehicle management office for registration was quite exhausting.
然后上车管所备案就很累了啊
It really wore me out.
弄得我很辛苦啊
So, to talk about it,
所以来讲的话
sometimes in life, what's crucial is the experience.
人生有的时候呢重要的是体验啊
After experiencing it, it turns out to be just that.
体验过后呢也就那么回事啊
So I think learning to ride a motorcycle or drive a car is still useful.
所以呢我觉得但是学摩托学汽车呢还是有用
Because in some cities and countries, you can go on motorcycle trips.
因为有些城市有些国家你是可以摩旅的
For example, Canada.
比如加拿大
For example, France.
比如法国
The two places where I went to school
我这两个上过学的地方
I can actually do motorcycle touring at both
我其实都可以摩旅啊
I'm quite happy about it
我挺开心的
Motorcycle touring is different from a road trip
摩旅跟这个自驾游不是一回事
But on a road trip, you can bring food
但是自驾游你可以带吃的
and toys
带玩的
and use it as a bed and go camping It's really great When it comes to motorcycle travel, you'll have to rough it out in the open. But it's manageable in China, I think it's different abroad. If you're roughing it out in urban areas, you might get attacked by thugs or something like that.
还可以当床 还可以露营 非常好 摩旅的话 你只能这个风餐露宿了 在中国还好 我觉得在国外 如果你要是在城市地区在风餐露宿的话 很容易被这个那个流氓啊什么的攻击
And it's not necessarily safe in the wild either.
在野外呢也不一定安全
You know,
知道吧
you might even get checked by the police.
有可能会被警察查
Well, you know
有可能那什么
unlike our area which has these highway service areas
不像咱们这块还会这个高速服务区
sometimes they let you
有的时候还会让你在这个
some places even allow you to camp and so on
有些地方还可以让你扎营啊之类的啊
after all, it's not a socialist country
毕竟毕竟不是社会主义国家
they don't care as much about the common people
他没有那么在意老百姓啊
so that's the difference
所以这是不一样的
and I think if you really love buying cars
嗯然后我觉得如果大家要是啊特别喜欢买车
or really love buying motorcycles
特别喜欢买摩托的话
Actually, getting one at a reasonable price would be fine.
其实买一个价格适中的就可以了
Because my ultimate goal is to not work.
因为我最终目的呢就是不上班
Your ultimate goal might be to enjoy life.
你们的最终目的可能就是享受人生啊
Enjoy life.
享受人生
Spending the money in advance,
提前把钱花了
you’ll have to work later.
你以后就得上班
for a long time,
上到很长时间
and there’s no guarantee you’ll even have a job.
还未必有班上
I choose to explain it this way.
我呢选择这样来讲的话
It's my choice
就是我的选择
My happiness is limited, though
我的快乐是有限的啊
I applied for a Japanese visa but didn't go
申请了日本签证也不去啊
I applied for a Canadian visa but didn't go
申请了加拿大签证也不去
I applied for a U.S. visa but didn't go
申请了美国签证也不去
Just having it is enough
就是有就行了
Knowing I can go whenever I want is enough Other things are unnecessary So that's how it is Everyone's sensory experiences are different. Don't let me dictate how you should live your life. Of course, As everyone knows, Not working is a great source of happiness.
知道自己随时能去就行了 别的东西没有必要了 所以这个东西就是这样啊 每个人的感觉体验不一样 也不要让我指导你怎么生活啊 当然来讲的话 大家知道呃 不上班就是一种非常大的快乐
When you're not working, you have a lot of time for creativity.
不上班你会有很多的时间用来创作啊
Well, it's kind of like living off your parents.
嗯其实就跟啃老差不多
Except I'm the one paying my parents.
只不过是我给我爸妈发工资
You guys probably get money from your parents.
你们可能是从爸妈那领钱
It just feels different
就是感觉是不一样的
But as you all know, my previous advice was that
但是我大家知道我之前的建议就是说
If your state over the past couple of years hasn't been quite right
如果你这两年的状态不是特别对的话
You see, the advice I give to young people and those in their thirties
你看我给年轻人跟30多岁人
Is different from what I suggest to people in their forties
40多岁人的建议都不一样
To the younger crowd, I recommend focusing on further education
年轻人我是建议你还是升学的
Making education your priority
还是以升学为主
Regardless of the circumstances
然后无论怎么样的话
Go abroad and broaden your horizons
去海外看一看
For those in their thirties
30多岁的人
I suggest you try to take it easy
我就建议你尽量躺平一点
and save up your money
然后把自己的钱攒一攒
then start a second career
然后开始事业的第二春
For those in their forties
40多岁的人
if you still haven’t made it
如果你还是没混出来的话
I think it’s important to have a clear mind
我觉得就是要放空一个心态了啊
just live
能能能活
and make sure you’re happy
让自己活的很快乐就可以了啊
Young people can still strive for their goals.
年轻的人还可以去奔一奔
But I still stand by what I said.
但是我还是那句话
I've told everyone this before.
我就跟大家说了
Not in this video, though.
就是呃不是在这个视频里说的
But I mentioned it in other videos.
但是我是在其他视频里说的
If you're young and want to break through social barriers, learning French remains crucial. I want to remind everyone again in this video to study French diligently. Study French, indeed. Let's not even talk about going to France.
就是年轻人如果你想突破阶层的话 学法语仍然是非常重要的 再次在视频里提醒大家好好学法语 学法语唉 就别说去法国了
You'd be in Quebec right away.
就是你一步到位就到魁北克了对吧
And speaking of the entire country of Canada,
而且加拿大全境来讲
if you're fluent in French,
如果你法语好的话
it will give you a significant advantage.
会给你非常大的优势啊
Since I studied in Canada,
因为我在加拿大留的学吗
I'm definitely going to highlight the benefits of Canada.
所以我肯定是说加拿大的好处啊
Of course, Canada has its downsides too.
当然来讲加拿大也有不好的地方
For example, it's not easy to find a job.
比如说工作也不好找
But compared to the difficulty of finding it,
但是相比这种不好找来讲
there's no age or racial discrimination.
他没有年龄歧视跟种族歧视
These things just don't exist.
这些东西是没有的啊
Some people say,
有人说啊
you might forget your last name,
有你漏漏你的last name
but most companies don’t have these issues.
不大部分公司是没有这些东西的啊
They all promote fair competition.
他都要公平竞争啊
After all, I have looked for jobs there before,
毕竟我是在那边找过工作
so I know what it's like.
我知道还有东西来讲
It's because I think places like Canada
就是因为我觉得加拿大
Australia
澳大利亚这种地方
and New Zealand
还有新西兰
have been changing their immigration policies over the past couple of years
这两年他的移民政策在变啊
and now everyone knows that Japan has tightened its business management visa requirements
知道大家现在日本经营管理签又收紧了
so I often advise young people
所以很多时候我建议年轻人啊
especially those in their twenties
特别20多岁
whose parents are still young
你们父母还年轻
to consider going abroad
你可以出去
Then choose
然后选择
Then go early
然后早点去
Well
那什么
We people in our forties
我们40多岁的人
Honestly, after we leave, it's a matter of life and death It's a time when our parents really need us We're leaving now That wouldn't be appropriate So there's a possibility that For example, after your parents leave we can leave then This is a more suitable approach
说实在走了以后就是面临一个生离死别 就有可能就爸妈很需要我们的年纪 我们走了哈 这就很不合适 所以有可能说啊 比如说等爸妈走了以后 我们再走 这是一种比较合适的方法
But how do you know when your parents will leave?
但是你你怎么知道你爸妈什么时候走呢
You might be 40
你可能40岁
You might be 60
你可能60岁啊
Or even 30, and it could be different
你可能30岁都不一样了
So this situation is about your parents leaving while they are still young
所以这个东西就是你爸妈很年轻就走了
At 30, would you still feel like you’re living a good life?
你30岁你觉得你活的还痛快吗
Not necessarily.
不一定的啊
So when people talk about someone who has a shallow connection with their relatives,
所以来讲人们说六亲这个缘浅的人呢
it actually means they can start a new life anywhere.
其实啊可以重新在任何地方开启自己的人生
Often, you might say, 'Oh, I don't have these things right now.',
很多时候你们就说哎呀我现在没有这些东西
I don't have a car,
我没有车
I don't have a house,
没有房子
but you need to realize that without a car,
你要知道你没有车
nobody can hold you back.
就没有人去限制你了
You don't have children
你没有孩子
You're not married
没有婚姻
So no one will hold you back
就没有人去束缚你了
If you want to go abroad, you can leave anytime
你想出国就随时可以走
Without parents
没有父母
There's even less restriction on you
他更没人限制你了
Of course, you might say that many people still tell me I'll lose my source of income
当然你说你很多人还说我经济来源就没有了啊
That's true
这是肯定的
So the more you have
所以来讲你拥有的越多
Actually, the more you are restricted
其实你越是被限制住
Look, if I go abroad once
你看我要是出一次国
I'm worried about what will happen to my son
我在想我儿子怎么办啊
What if my dad gets sick
我爸生病了怎么办
Who can I turn to What if my mom gets sick There needs to be someone to rely on Whether it's an older brother, sister, relative, or friend You need to have someone to entrust your child to What to do How to connect How to return it and such I need to discuss with my ex-wife
找谁 我妈生病了怎么办 都得有托付啊 甭管是哥哥姐姐还是亲戚还是朋友之类 你得有托付孩子啊 怎么办 怎么接 怎么送回去之类的 得跟我前妻商量
Right?
对不对
So the more you have of this
所以这个你拥有的越多
The more you have to consider
你考虑的越越多啊
You talk about having 3000 beauties in your harem
你说说我后宫佳丽3000
How do you settle them all?'
你怎么安顿人家呀
Right?
对不对
You can't possibly know everyone.
你总不能认识
And then be abandoned.
完了以后就给人抛弃了
Right?
对不对
You have to settle them down.
你肯定要安顿人家
Buy them a house.
得给人买套房
Take good care of them.
得给人养的好好的
Plump and healthy.
胖胖的
Isn't it?
是不是
So the more you have, the more complications there are.
所以这很多东西你拥有的越多啊
Having cars, houses, yachts, and planes.
拥有车房游艇飞机
How much money do you have to spend on them?
你要为这个要消耗多少钱
How much effort do you have to put in?
消耗多少精力
This is a significant burden.
这个是很大的
So I suggest that the less you own, the better.
所以我建议大家拥有的越少啊
The happier you'll be.
越快乐
This way, you have fewer ties.
这样就没有什么牵绊
And having more possessions doesn't necessarily mean more happiness.
而且拥有的东西多了来讲未必是快乐
So when I have to own something, I choose the cheaper option.
所以我啊在非拥有不可的情况下
Because I think owning a luxury car is really a burden.
我就选择便宜的
And the more outstanding your children are, the more you can't let go of them.
因为我觉得拥有的好车啊真的是一个累赘
The more distant the relationship becomes.
拥有的孩子说实在的越优秀
For example, my relationship with my father isn't good.
你越是离不开他
My relationship with my mother isn't good either.
你越是那什么到时关系不近的那种人
I can choose not to see them, and that's actually a blessing.
比如说我跟我父亲的关系不好
Always look at the best side of things. The side that benefits you the most. Don't dwell on the negative aspects. This way, you can be very happy. As I always say, The more you own, the less happy you might be.
跟我母亲关系不好 我倒是可以不看他们 其实这是一种祝福啊 所有的时候都把事物看最好 最有利于自己的那一方面 不要去想负面的那一方面啊
The more you have, the more of a burden it can become.
这样来讲你就能做的很快乐了啊
You may have to invest a lot of time and energy into it.
还是那句话
Without it, you can just walk away.
你拥有的越多未必快乐
Like me, I have a cat,
拥有的多了
A car,
很可能就是累赘
A motorcycle,
很可能你要为这付出时间和精力
A house,
没有的话
Parents,
你拔腿就走啊
And a son.
你像我还有猫啊
Do you think I can go out and play?
还有车
And have a good time?
还有摩托
Impossible.
还有房子
Right?
还有父母
When the child is far away,
还有儿子
The mother worries.
你说我能出去玩的
You have all sorts of concerns in your heart.
玩的痛快了吗
So you can't live your life to the fullest.
不可能
If you have a distant relationship with your family,
对不对
No wife,
儿行千里
No children,
母担忧
You are a free person.
你心中都是各种各样的牵挂
No house,
所以你就没有办法活好自己的人生了
No car,
如果你六亲缘浅
You are a born adventurer.
没有媳妇儿啊
You can wander anywhere,
没有孩子啊
And no one will miss you.
是无敌之人
That's a pretty good thing.
又没有房
As they say, I would give up everything I have now to bring my father back to life.
有没有车
That's a remarkable thing.
你是一个天生的冒险家
I feel that family is the most important thing to me.
你可以去任意地方流浪
Maybe I don't need to go out and play.
也不会有人惦记你
So this is how I save money.
这是挺好的一件事情
So it's like what Lan Zhanfei said.
所以来讲就像蓝战非那话说的似的
I’d rather trade everything I have now for my dad to come back to life.
就我宁可用现在所有的一切换我爸再活过来啊
This thing is truly remarkable.
这个东西是非常了不起的
I also feel that family ties are important to me
我也觉得亲情这个东西对我来讲
It might be the heaviest one.
可能是最重的啊
Going out to play might not be necessary. So this is how I save money.
出去玩可能倒没必要了 所以这就是我省钱的方式